Okay, this is linear algebra lecture
nine and this is a key lecture. This is
where we get these ideas of
linear independence. When a bunch of
vectors are independent
or dependent, that's the opposite.
Uh the space they span,
a basis for a subspace or a basis for a
vector space, that's a central idea. And
then the dimension of that subspace. So
this is the day that those words get
assigned clear meanings and emphasize
that we talk about
a bunch of vectors being independent.
Wouldn't talk about a matrix being
independent, a bunch of vectors being
independent, a bunch of vectors spanning
a space, a bunch of vectors being a
basis, and the dimension is some number.
Okay. So what are the definitions? Can I
begin with a fact a highly important
fact that uh I didn't call directly
attention to earlier. Suppose I have a
matrix
and I look at ax equals z.
Suppose the matrix has a lot of columns
so that n is bigger than m. So, I'm
looking at n equations. I'm sorry, m
equations. A small number of equations,
m and more unknowns. I have more
unknowns than equations.
Let me write that down. More unknowns
than equations.
More
unknown x's
than equations.
Then
then the conclusion is that there's
something in the null space of a
other than just the zero vector. The
conclusion is there are some nonzero
x's such that ax is zero. There are some
special solutions and why we know why.
I mean it sort of like seems like a
reasonable thing. more unknowns than
equations
then it seems reasonable that we can
solve them. But we have a a clear
algorithm
which starts with a system and does
elimination
gets the thing into an echelon form with
some pivots and pivot columns
and possibly some free columns that
don't have pivots. And the point is here
there will be some free columns. The
reason so the reason is
there must there will be
free variables at least one.
That's the reason
that we we now have this a complete uh
algorithm complete systematic way to say
okay we take the system ax equals zero
we row reduce we identify the free
variables and since there are n
variables
and at most m pivots there will be some
free variables at least one at least n
minus m in fact left over and those
variables I can assign nonzero values
to. I don't have to set those to zero. I
can take them to be one or whatever I
like and then I can solve for the pivot
variables. So then it gives me a
solution to ax equals z and it's a
solution that isn't all zeros.
So uh that's a c that's a important
point that we'll use now in this
lecture.
So now I want to say what does it mean
for a bunch of vectors to be
independent. Okay. So this is like the
background that we know. Now I want to
speak about independence.
Okay,
let's see.
I can give you the the the
uh abstract definition and I will but I
would also like to give you the direct
meaning when
my so the question is when vectors
x1
x2 up to suppose I have n vectors are
independent
If now I have to give you
or linearly independent
I'll I'll often just say and write
independent for short if okay let I'll
give you the full definition these are
just vectors in some vector space I can
take combinations of them the question
is do any combinations give zero
if some combination of those vectors
gives the zero vector
other than the combination of all zeros.
Then they're dependent.
They're independent if no
combination
gives
the zero vector
and then I have I'll have to put in and
accept
the
zero
combination. So what do I mean by that?
No combination gives the zero vector.
Any combination C1 X1 + C2 X2 + plus C N
XN
is not zero
except for the zero combination. This is
when all the C's all the C's are zero.
Then of course
that combination I I'm I know I'll get
zero. But the the question is does any
other combination give zero? If not
then the vectors are independent. If
some other combination does give zero
the vectors are dependent. Okay let's
just take examples.
Suppose I'm in
say in two-dimensional space.
Okay I give you I I'd like to first take
an example. Let me take an example where
I have a vector and twice that vector.
So that's two vectors V and 2V. Are
those dependent or independent?
Those are dependent for sure. Right?
There's a combin one vector is twice the
other. One vector is twice as long as
the other. So if the word dependent
means anything, these should be
dependent. And they are. And in fact, I
would take two of the first. So here's
here's a vector V and the other guy is a
vector 2V. That's my So there's a vector
V1 and my ve my next vector V2 is 2 V1.
Of course, those are dependent because
two of these first vectors minus the
second vector is zero. That's a
combination of these two vectors that
gives the zero vector. Okay, that was
clear. Suppose suppose I have a vector.
Here's another example. It's easy
example. Suppose I have a vector and the
other guy is the zero vector. Suppose I
have a vector v1 and v2 is the zero
vector. Then are those vectors dependent
or independent?
They're dependent. Again,
you could say, well, this guy is zero
times that one. This one is some
combination of those. But let me write
it the other way. Let me say what what
combination how many V1s and how many
V2s shall I take to get the zero vector?
If if v_sub_1 is like the vector 21 and
v2 is the zero vector 0 0 then I would
like to show that some combination of
those gives the zero vector. What shall
I take? How many v1's shall I take?
Zero of them. Yeah. No. Take no v1s. But
how many v2s?
Six. Okay.
or five.
Then in other words, the point is if the
zero vectors in there, if the zero if if
one of these vectors is the zero vector,
independence is dead, right? If one of
those vectors is the zero vector, then I
could always take
include that one and none of the others
and I would get the zero answer and I
would show dependence. Okay. Now uh let
me let me finally draw an example where
they will be independent. Suppose that's
v1 and that's v2.
Those are surely independent right. Any
combination of v_sub_1 and v2 uh will
not be zero except uh the zero
combination. So those would be
independent. But now let me let me stick
in a third vector v3.
independent or dependent. Now those
three vectors. So now n is three. Here
I'm in two-dimensional space. Whatever
I'm in the plane I have three vectors
that I didn't draw so carefully. I
didn't even tell you what exactly they
were. But what's this answer on
dependent or independent?
Dependent. Why? How do I know the those
are dependent?
How do I know that some combination of
vub1, v2 and v3 gives me the zero
vector?
I know because of that that's the that's
the uh
key fact
that tells me that three vectors in the
plane have to be dependent. Why is that?
What's the connection between the
dependence of these three vectors and
that fact? Okay, so here's the
connection. I take the matrix A
that has V1 in its first column,
V2 in its second column, V3 in its third
column.
So it's got three columns. And V1, I
don't know, that looks like about 21 to
me. V2 looks like it might be one two.
V3 looks like it might be maybe two
maybe two and a half
minus one.
Okay, those are three. Those are my
three vectors and I put them in the
columns of A.
Now that matrix A is 2x3. It fits this
pattern that where we know we've got
extra variables. We know we have some
free variables. We know that there's
some combination and let me instead of
X's, let me call them C1, C2, and C3
that gives the zero vector.
Sorry that my little bit of art got in
the way. Do you see the point? When I
have a matrix,
I'm interested in whether its columns
are dependent or independent.
The columns are dependent if there is
something in the null space. The columns
are dependent because this this thing in
the null space says that C1 of that plus
C2 of that plus C3 of this is zero. So
in other words, I can go out some V1 out
some more V2 back on V3 and end up zero.
Okay. So let
here I've given the general abstract
definition but let me repeat that
definition. So this is like repeat
when
for
when the v1 let me call them v's now v1
up to vn are the columns
of a matrix a
in other words this is telling me that
if I'm in if I'm in n if I'm in uh md
dimensional space like two-dimensional
space in the example. I can answer the
dependence independence question
directly
by putting those vectors in the columns
of a matrix. Then they independent. They
are independent.
Independent
if
the null space of A
of A is what?
If I have a bunch of columns in a
matrix,
I'm looking at their combinations, but
that's just A times
the vector of C's
and the ve and these columns will be
independent if the null space of A is
only the zero vector is only is the zero
vector.
They are dependent
if there's something else in there. If
there's something else in the null
space, if a * c gives the zero vector
for some nonzero
vector c in the null space,
then they're dependent because that's
telling me a combination of the columns
gives the zero column. I I I think
you're with me because we've seen like
lecture after lecture we're looking at
the combinations of the columns and
asking do we get zero or don't we and
now we're giving the official name
dependent if we do independent if we
don't so I could express this in other
words now I could say the rank what's
the rank in this independent case the
rank R of of the matrix in the case of
independent columns is
so the columns are independent.
So how many pivot columns have I got?
All in all the columns would be pivot
columns
because free columns are telling me that
they're a combination of earlier
columns. So this would be the case where
the rank is n. This would be the case
where the rank is smaller than n.
So in this case the rank is n and the
null space of a is only the zero vector
and no free variables. No free
variables.
And this is the case. Yes. free
variables
if you'll allow me to stretch the
English language that far. Uh that's the
case where we have
um
a combination that gives the zero
column. So I I'm often interested in the
case when my vectors are popped into a
matrix.
So the the definition over there of
independence didn't talk about any
matrix.
The vectors didn't have to be vectors in
n-dimensional space. And I I want to
give it some examples of vectors that
aren't what you think of immediately as
vectors. But most of the time this is
the we the vectors we think of are
columns
and we can put them in a matrix and then
independence or dependence comes back to
the null space.
Okay. So that's the idea of
independence.
Can I just uh
yeah let me let me go on to spanning a
space.
What does it mean for a bunch of vectors
to span a space?
Well, actually, we've seen it already.
You remember if if we had a columns in a
matrix,
we took all their combinations
and that gave us the column space.
Those vectors that we started with span
that column space. So spanning a space
means
so let me move that important stuff
right up.
Okay. So vectors
let me call them say V1 up to I'll use
some different letter say V L
span
a space
a subspace
or just a vector space I could say span
a space means
means
The space
consists of
all
combinations
of those vectors.
That that's exactly what we did with the
column space.
So now I could say in shorthand the
columns of a matrix span the column
space.
So remember it's a bunch of vectors that
have this property that they span a
space. And actually
if I give you a bunch of vectors and say
okay let s be the space that they span.
In other words let s contain all their
combinations.
that space s will be the smallest space
with those vectors in it. Right? Because
any space with those vectors in it must
have all the combinations of those
vectors in it. And if I stop there,
then I've got the smallest space and
that's the space that they span. Okay?
So I'm just rather than uh needing to
say take all linear combinations and put
them in a space, I'm I'm compressing
that
into the word span.
Straightforward.
Okay.
So if I think of a of the column space
of a matrix,
I've got I've got their So I start with
the columns. I take all their
combinations that gives me the column
space. They span the column space. Now,
are they independent?
Maybe yes, maybe no.
It depends on the particular columns
that went into that matrix.
But obviously, I'm highly interested in
a set of vectors
that spans the space and is independent.
That's that means like I've got the
right number of vectors.
If I didn't have all of them, I wouldn't
have my whole space.
If I had more than that, they probably
wouldn't they wouldn't be independent.
So like basis and that's the word that's
coming is just right. So here let me put
what that word means. A basis
for a vector for a vector space is
is a is a sequence of vectors
shall I call them v1 v2
up to let me say v d now I'll stop with
that letters that has two properties.
I've got enough vectors and not too
many. It's a natural idea of a basis. So
a basis is a bunch of vectors in the
space
and it's a so it's a sequence of vectors
with two properties with
two properties.
One,
they are independent.
And two,
you know what's coming? They span the
space.
Okay,
let me take
So time for examples of course.
So I'm asking you now to put definition
one the definition of independence
together with definition two and let's
look at examples because this is this
combination means the set of of vectors
I have is just right and that so that
this idea of a basis will be central.
I'll always be asking you now for a
basis. Whenever I look at a subspace,
if I ask you for if you give me a basis
for that subspace, you've told me what
it is. You've told me everything I need
to know about that subspace. Those I
take their combinations and I know that
I need all the combinations. Okay.
Examples.
Okay. So, examples of a basis. Let me
start with two-dimensional space.
Suppose the the space say example
the space is
uh let's make it R3
real threedimensional space
give me one basis one basis is
so I want some vectors
because if I ask you for a basis I'm
asking you for vectors a little list of
vectors
and
it should be just right. So what would
be a basis for three-dimensional space?
Well, the first basis that comes to
mind, why don't we write that down? The
first basis that comes to mind is this
vector,
this vector,
and this vector.
Okay, that's one basis.
Not the only basis. That's going to be
my point.
But let's just see. Yes, that's a basis.
Is every are those vectors independent?
So that's the like the X, Y, and Z axis.
So if those are not independent, we're
in trouble. Certainly they are. Take a
combination C1 of this vector plus C2 of
this vector plus C3 of that vector and
try to make it give the zero vector.
What are the C's?
If C1 of that plus C2 of that plus C3 of
that gives me 0 0, then the C's are all
zero. Right? So that's the test for
independence
in the language of matrices.
which was under that board. I could make
those the columns of a matrix. Well, it
would be the identity matrix.
Then I would ask what's the null space
of the identity matrix. And you would
say it's only the zero vector. And I
would say fine then the columns are
independent.
The only thing the identity times a
vector giving zero the only ve vector
that does that is zero. Okay.
Now, that's not the only basis. Far from
it. Tell me another basis. A second
basis. Another basis.
So,
uh, give me well, I'll just start it
out. One, one, two,
uh, 225.
Uh suppose I stop there.
Have has that has that see has that have
has that little bunch of vectors got the
properties that I'm asking for in a
basis for R3? We're we're looking for a
basis for R3. Are they independent,
those two column vectors? Yes. Do they
span R3?
No. Our feeling is no. Our feeling is
no. Our feeling is that there's some
vectors in R3 that are not combinations
of those. Okay. So suppose I add in a I
need another vector then because they
these two don't span the space. Okay.
Now it would be foolish for me to put in
337 right as the third vector.
That would be a goof because that if I
put in 337, those vectors would be
dependent, right? If I put in 337, it
would be the sum of those two. It would
lie in the same plane as those. It
wouldn't be independent. I wouldn't I
wouldn't I my attempt to create a basis
would be dead. But if I take So what
vector can I take?
I can take any vector that's not in that
plane. Let me try. I I hope that 338
would do it.
At least it's not the sum of those two
vectors. But I believe that's a basis.
And what's the what's the test then for
that to be a basis? What? Because I just
picked those numbers. And if I had
picked uh 57
minus14,
how would we know do we have a basis or
don't we?
You would put them in the columns of a
matrix
and you would do elimination row
reduction and you would see do you get
any
free variables or are all the columns
pivot columns? Well, now actually we
have a square. The matrix would be 3x3.
So, so what's the test on the matrix
then?
The matrix. So, so in this case when I
when my space is R3 and I have three
vectors,
my matrix is square.
And
what am I asking about that matrix in
order for those columns to be a basis?
So the so in this in this for Rn
if I have n vectors
give a basis.
If
the n byn matrix
with those columns
with
those columns
is what
what's what's the requirement on that
matrix?
Invertible. Right. Right. The matrix
should be invertible for a square
matrix. That's the that's the perfect
answer is invertible.
So that's when that's when the space is
is is the whole space Rn.
Let me let me be sure I I'm with you're
with me here. Let me remove that.
Are those two vectors a basis for
any space at all?
Is there a vector space that those
really are a basis for? Those that pair
of vectors, this guy and this one 112
and 225. Is there a space for which
that's a basis?
Sure, they're independent.
So they satisfy the first requirement.
So what space shall I take for them to
be a basis of? What spaces will they be
a basis for?
the one they span they're combinations
if it's a plane right it will be a plane
inside R3 so if I take this vector 112
say it goes there and this vector 225
say it goes there those are a basis for
because they span a plane
and they're a basis for the plane
because they're independent if I stick
in some third guy like 337 which is in
the plane
Suppose I put in try to put in 337 then
the three vectors would still span the
plane but they wouldn't be a basis
anymore because they're not independent
anymore. Okay. So uh we're looking at
the question of so again
a the case with in independent columns
is the case where the column vectors
span the column space. They're
independent so they're a basis for the
column space. Okay. So now there's one
bit of intuition.
Let me go back to all of Rn.
So where I put 338.
Okay. The first message is that the
basis is not unique. Right? There's
zillions of bases. I take any invertible
3x3 matrix. its columns are a basis for
R3.
The column space is R3. And if those if
that matrix is invertible, those columns
are independent. I've got a basis for
R3. So there are many many bases, but
there is something
in common for all those bases.
There's something that this basis shares
with that basis and every other basis
for R3.
And what's that?
Well, you saw it coming because when I
stopped here
and asked if that was a basis for R3,
you said no. And I know that you said no
because you knew there weren't enough
vectors there.
And the great fact is that there are
many, many bases, but let me put in
somebody else just for
variety.
There are many, many bases, but they all
have the same number of vectors.
If we're talking about the space R3,
then that number of vectors is three.
If we're talking about the space Rn,
then that number of vectors is N.
If we're talking about some other space,
the column space of some matrix
or the null space of some matrix or some
other space that we haven't even thought
of.
Then that still is true that every basis
that there are lots of bases but every
basis has the same number of vectors.
Let me write that great fact down.
every
basis we're we're given a space given
a space
R3 or Rn or some other column space of a
matrix or the null space of a matrix or
some other vector space then the great
fact is that every basis
for the for the space
has
the same
number
of vectors.
If one basis has six vectors, then every
other basis has six vectors.
So that number six is telling me like
it's telling me how big is the space.
It's telling me how many vectors do I
have to have to have a basis.
And of course, we're seeing it this way.
That number six, if we had seven vectors
and we've got too many. If we have five
vectors, we haven't got enough.
Six is sort of like just right for
whatever space that is. And what do we
call that number? That number is now I'm
ready for the last definition today.
It's the dimension
of that space. So every basis for a
space has the same number of vectors in
it. Not the same vectors,
all sorts of bases, but the same number
of vectors is always the same. And that
number is the dimension. This is
definition.
This number is the dimension.
of the space.
Okay.
Okay,
let's do some examples
because now we got definitions. Let me
repeat the four things, the four words
that have now got defined. Independence
that looks at combinations not being
zero.
Spanning that looks at all the
combinations. Basis that's the one that
combines independence and spanning. And
now we've got the idea of the dimension
of a space. It's the number of vectors
in any basis because all bases have the
same number. Okay. Let's let's take
examples.
Suppose I take
uh my space is examples. Now space is
the say the column space of this matrix.
Let me let me write down a matrix.
1 one 2 one two and I'll just to make it
clear I'll take the sum there 3 2 3 and
let me take the sum of all oh let me put
in one yeah I'll put in 11 one again
okay
so that's four vectors
okay do they span the column space of
that matrix
let me repeat do They span the column
space of that matrix. Yes, by definition
that's what the column space where it
comes from. Are they a basis for the
column space? Are they independent?
No, they're not independent. There's
something in that null space.
Maybe we can. So, let's look at the null
space of the matrix.
Tell me a vector that's in the null
space of that matrix.
So I'm looking for some vector that
combines those columns and produces the
zero column.
Or in other words, I'm looking for
solutions to ax= z. So so tell me a
vector in the null space.
Maybe well this was this column was that
one plus that one. So maybe if I have
one of those and minus one of those that
would be a vector in the null space.
So you've already told me now are those
vectors independent? The answer is those
column vectors. The answer is no. Right?
They're not independent because ah you
knew they weren't independent anyway.
Minus one of this minus one of this plus
one of this zero of that is the zero
vector. Okay.
Okay. So they're not independent. They
span but they're not independent. Tell
me
a basis
for that column space.
What's a basis for the column space?
These are all the questions that the
homework asks, the quizzes asked, the
final exam will ask. Find a basis for
the column space of this matrix.
Okay.
Now, there's many answers, but give me
the most natural answer.
columns
one and two. Columns one and two. That's
the natural answer. Those are the pivot
columns because I mean we we begin
systematically. We look at the first
column. It's okay. We can put that in
the basis. We look at the second column.
It's okay. We can put that in the basis.
The third column we can't put in the
basis. The fourth column we
can't again. So the rank of the matrix
is
what's the rank of our matrix? Two. Two.
And and now that rank is also we now
have another word. We we have a great
theorem here. The rank of A
that rank R
is the number of pivot columns
and it's also
well so now please use my new word
this it's the number two of course two
is the rank of my matrix. It's the
number of pivot columns. Those pivot
columns form a basis of course. So
what's two?
It's the dimension.
The rank of A, the number of pivot
columns is the dimension
of
the column space. Of
course, you say it had to be right. But
just watch look for one moment at the
the language, the way the English words
get involved here. I take the rank of a
matrix.
the rank of a matrix.
It's a number of columns and it's the
dimension of
not the dimension of the matrix. That's
what I want to say. It's the dimension
of a space, a subspace, the column
space.
Do do you see I I don't take the
dimension of A. That's not what I want.
I'm looking for the dimension of the
column space of A. If you use those
words right, it shows you got the idea
right.
Similarly, here I don't talk about the
rank of a subspace.
It's a matrix that has a rank. I talk
about the rank of a matrix. And it the
beauty is that these definitions just
merge so that the rank of a matrix is
the dimension of its column space. And
in this example, it's two. And then the
further question is what's a basis? And
the first two columns are a basis. Tell
me another basis. Another basis for the
column space. You see, I just keep
hammering away. I apologize, but it's I
have to be sure you have the idea of
basis. Tell me another basis for the
column space.
Well, you could take columns one and
three.
That would be a basis for the column
space. or columns two and three would be
a basis or columns two and four or me
another basis that's not made out of
those columns at all.
So well I guess I'm giving you
infinitely many possibilities so I can't
expect a unanimous answer here. I tell
you let's look at another basis though.
I'll just because it's only one out of
zillions. I'm going to put it down and
I'm going to erase it. Another basis for
the column space
would be
uh let's see I'll put in some things
that are not there. say, "Oh, well, just
to make it my life easy, 222. That's in
the column space."
And uh that was sort of obvious. Let me
take the sum of those say 6 46
or the sum of all the columns 757. Why
not? That's in the column space.
Those are independent.
And I've got the number right. I've got
two. Actually, this is a key point.
If you know the dimension of the space
you're working with, and we know that
this column, we know that the dimension
dime the dimension of the column space
is two.
If you know the the dimension then then
uh
and we have a couple of vectors that are
independent
they'll automatically be a basis. If
we've got the number of vectors right,
two vectors in this case, then if
they're independent, they can't help but
span the space because if they didn't
span the space, there'd be a third guy
to help span the space.
But it couldn't be independent. So it it
just has to be
independent if we've got the numbers
right
and they span. Okay, very good. So you
got the dimension of a space. So this
was another basis that I just invented.
Okay. Now,
now I get to ask you about the null
space.
What's the dimension of the null space?
So we we got a great fact there. The
dimension
of the column space is the rank.
Now I want to ask you about the null
space. That's the other
part of the lecture and it'll go on to
the next lecture.
Okay.
So we know the dimension of the column
space is two. The rank. What about the
null space? This is a vector in the null
space. Are there other vectors in the
null space?
Yes or no? Yes. So this isn't a basis
because it's doesn't span. Right?
There's more in the null space than
we've got so far. I need another vector
at least. So tell me another vector in
the null space.
Well, the natural choice, the choice you
naturally think of is I'm going on to
the fourth column.
I'm letting that free variable be a one
and that free variable be a zero. And
I'm asking, is that fourth column a
combination of my pivot columns? Yes, it
is. And it's
that will do.
So what I've written there are actually
the two special solutions, right? I took
the two free variables free and free.
I gave them the values one zero or 01. I
figured out the rest.
So do do you see? Let me just say it in
words. this vector, these vectors in the
null space are telling me, they're
telling me the combinations of the
columns that give zero. They're telling
me
in what way the the columns are
dependent. That's what the null space is
doing. Have I got enough now?
And what's the null space? Now, we have
to think about the null space.
These are two vectors in the null space.
They're independent. Are they a basis
for the null space? What's the dimension
of the null space? You see that those
questions just keep coming up all the
time.
Are they a basis for the null space? You
can tell me the answer even though we
haven't written out a proof of that. Can
you yes or no? Do these two special
solutions form a basis for the null
space? In other words, does the null
space consist of all combinations of
those two guys? Yes or no? Yes. Yes.
The null space is two-dimensional. The
null space, the dimension of the null
space is the number of free variables.
So the dimension of the null space
is the number of free variables
and at the last second give me the
formula.
This is then the key formula that we
know how many free variables are there
in terms of r the rank m the number of
rows n the number of columns
what do we get we have n columns
r of them are pivot columns so n minus r
is the number of free columns free
variables and now it's the dimension of
the null space. Okay, that's great.
That's the key spaces, their bases, and
their dimensions. Thanks,